<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Magick &amp; astrology vindicated from those false aspersions and calumnies, which the ignorance of some hath cast upon them. In which is contained true definitions of the said arts, and the justification of their practise, proved by the authority of Scripture, and the experience of ancient and modern authors. With observations from several remarkable conjunctions and apparitions: as those three suns that appeared before the Kings death, &amp;c. / Impartially communicated for the publique good. By Hardick Warren, a well-wisher to the most secret occult arts and learning.</title>
            <author>Warren, Hardick.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97219</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W971</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E623_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206369</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865530</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865530</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117775</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97219)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117775)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 96:E623[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Magick &amp; astrology vindicated from those false aspersions and calumnies, which the ignorance of some hath cast upon them. In which is contained true definitions of the said arts, and the justification of their practise, proved by the authority of Scripture, and the experience of ancient and modern authors. With observations from several remarkable conjunctions and apparitions: as those three suns that appeared before the Kings death, &amp;c. / Impartially communicated for the publique good. By Hardick Warren, a well-wisher to the most secret occult arts and learning.</title>
                  <author>Warren, Hardick.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed J.M. for N. Brook at the Angel and Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copy: "Feb: 6 1650", the 51 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Magic --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117775:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Magick &amp; Aſtrology VINDICATED From thoſe Falſe Aſperſions and Calumnies, which the Ignorance of ſome hath caſt upon them.</p>
            <p>In which is contained true Definitions of the ſaid Arts, and the Juſtification of their Practiſe, proved by the Authority of Scripture, and the Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of Ancient and Modern Authors.</p>
            <p>With Obſervations from ſeveral remarkable Conjunctions and Apparitions: As thoſe <hi>Three Suns</hi> that appeared before the Kings Death, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Impartially communicated for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Good.</p>
            <p>By HARDICK WARREN, A Well-wiſher to the moſt ſecret Occult Arts and Learning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed <hi>J. M.</hi> for <hi>N. Brook</hi> at the Angel in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:117775:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117775:2"/>
            <head>To the Author M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>H. W.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>WHen Reaſon, Fancy, Wit, and Grace,</l>
            <l>In tender years, take each their place,</l>
            <l>Theſe make the man; all theſe I ſee</l>
            <l>Coneur in this thy Book and thee:</l>
            <l>Dear Friend, I'le vow thy Book I muſt call,</l>
            <l>Not Sublunary, but Celeſtial;</l>
            <l>For ſure th' Intelligences mov'd thy Brain,</l>
            <l>And were the <hi>Primum Mobile</hi> of thy ſtrain;</l>
            <l>Thy Star, a glorious Sun, and gives more light</l>
            <l>Then can b' obſcur'd by fouleſt Envies ſpight.</l>
            <l>And for thy Book, the praiſe it gets of mine</l>
            <l>Is only this, it's excellent, good, and thine.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>By W. A.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <l>COme Carping <hi>Momus,</hi> ſpend thy ſpleen in vain,</l>
            <l>Pour out thy Envy like the Ocean main,</l>
            <l>And ſee if thou canſt crown the Hyſtery</l>
            <l>Of this ſmall Piece with its Divinity,</l>
            <l>And Natures pureſt Workings, which I own</l>
            <l>With the first Cauſe, all which is clearly ſhown</l>
            <l>In this ſame Book, all which appears to me</l>
            <l>In the pure Art of <hi>Magick</hi> and <hi>Aſtrologie:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>So it ſhall have my ſerious approbation;</l>
            <l>I have the Book, but it my admiration.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>By J. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:117775:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou art in this following Treatiſe (though but ſmall) informed with the ſubſtantial Grounds of thoſe (almoſt infinite Arts) to wit, of Magick and Aſtrology, both which, by reaſon of a fatal deprivation of theſe latter times, and the moſt of men, have fallen under the moſt deteſtable Notions that it were poſſible to brand them withall; the which did ariſe by reaſon of thoſe many wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and abominable Practiſes of ſome men, whoſe whole Soul hath been let forth to its Liberty to converſe with the Reprobate Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Darkneſs, whoſe Diabolical Practiſes have been by them ſhrouded under the Name of Magick and Aſtrology, when as indeed they have not in the leaſt meaſure been acquainted with the true knowledg either of the Creator, or of thoſe moſt glorious reſults of his wiſdom and power in thoſe many &amp; excellent Creatures, which are the Images of his Glory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and in the which (more then the moſt of men are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with) he takes pleaſure to be conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant; for his delight is in the inhabitable parts
<pb facs="tcp:117775:3"/> of the Earth, and his chief Recreation (if I may ſo ſpeak without offence) amongſt the poor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Sons of men, whoſe love is ſuch, that he hath in a moſt condeſcending way wrapped himſelf about with the whole Creation, that none might be ignorant of his Excellency; and in this way many of thoſe Hermitick Spirits who renounced the vain beauty of the meaneſt of the Appearances of the World, came to have thoſe moſt excellent and admirable Manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which produce admiration in me, when I conſider that we who profeſs our ſelves to know and to converſe with our God in a more immediate way, yet come ſhort of ſome of thoſe holy Souls, who were ignorant of all but this indwelling of the firſt Cauſe in the creature. But I muſt expect, and that from thoſe that are not a little learned in their own Opinion, and no leſſe knowing in the Myſteries of God in their conceits, to be all to be Devil'd for my labour in this work; but to ſuch I ſay, that their groſs Ignorance ſhall be puniſhed with Tantalus tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and their Siſypus Robberies of us the Commonalty (under their ſpecious pretence of a divine Right) with an endleſs toyl. Reader, theſe are the Arts, and eſpecially that of Magick, which as to our Engliſh Nation hath worn the
<pb facs="tcp:117775:4"/> Ring of Gyges, and walked inviſible; but now thou heareſt it ſpeaking in thy own Dialect, not tyed in a Gardian knot of impoſſibilities, but may be experimented by thee, if thy ſecret Genus can but ſoar ſo high; but ſure I am, with pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted hands, and a fond conceit of thy ſelf in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of thy knowledg, thou art not able to do any thing in it; there is more divine correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency required then thou art aware of, or may be then thou art capable to receive: Thou muſt not expect with a ſwiniſh affection to draw ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Virtues with thy earthly gruntlings; no: if thou canſt attain a divine Rapture, and bring thy Soul and its Attendants from that dark Dungeon of Earth, and looſened from thoſe curſed Fetters of ſin, thou art the man which art fit to receive power from thoſe bleſſed Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligences, and mayſt do wonders in thy genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I have in the Magical part of this Treatiſe followed the method of that moſt admirable <hi>Agrippa,</hi> whoſe learned Works I do profeſs I honor above all the Books in the world, except the Sacred Writ: What I have writ is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to thoſe fond and fooliſh Doctrines of many old doting women, who that they might be thought to have a divine Power, that as <hi>Apu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leius</hi> ſaith, they can throw down the Heavens,
<pb facs="tcp:117775:4"/> lift up the Earth, harden Fountains, waſh away Mountains, raiſe up infernal Spirits, command Ghoſts, caſt down the Gods, extinguiſh the Stars, and enlighten even Hell it ſelf; whereof many I confeſs are as well of a falacious opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as ſuperſtitious diligence, and pernicious and deadly endeavor; for when that they cannot appear in publique under the practiſe of a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Diabolical Art, yet they are ſo audacious as to preſume to think that they are capable to cloke themſelves under the honorable Name of Magick; the which hath cauſed amongſt the moſt of men an inveterate hate to the very name, which is exceeding good and commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. I wiſh that thoſe who are but ſlenderly acquainted in the Principals thereof may not bring a diſhonor upon it by their boaſting of abilities to produce Wonders, and are not able to operate any thing but what is common to every Nature; it is ſuch a Myſtery that it is found out and attained but by a very few, but groſly abuſed almoſt of all.</p>
            <p>Therefore I commend this ſmall Treatiſe only to the true Sons of Minerva, who are alone able to judg of it, and whoſe Cenſure I only va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue; if any imperfection be in it, let this take off the blot of my diſhonor, to wit, my tender
<pb facs="tcp:117775:5"/> years, which indeed are not many, and the ſhortneſs of time that I have been converſant in the Study of this worthy Myſtery; and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo, but my being unacquainted with the way of publique Writing, it being the firſt that ever I attempted to publiſh, not being born to ſuch an end, but for a private Contemplation, for which end I compoſed it; but by reaſon of the exceeding importunity of a loving Friend, and a Well-wiſher with my ſelf to ſecret Learning, I was neceſſitated to give my aſſent, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting of it to the publike view; therefore ſuch as it is, thou haſt the benefit of it to peruſe; if thou receiveſt any advantage by it, I have the ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate of my ambition, and ſo ſhall be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine, <hi>H. W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Friendly Reader, I would entreat thee to rectifie theſe faults, which are not many, before thou peruſeſt the following Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>As in pag. 9 line 24 for ſober read Solar, p. 11. l 18. for ſober r. Solar, p. 12. l. 14. r. it paſſeth to the fancy, p. 13. l. 12. r. that he wrote, p. 14. l. 22. for Ayr, r. Ayry, and l. 36. for theſe r. thoſe, p. 16. l. 33. for Star r. Stars, p 20 l. 16, r. being in Conjunction, l. 22. for are r. were, p. 23. l. 1. r. with them then it was.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117775:5"/>
            <head>Magick &amp; Aſtrology VINDICATED From thoſe falſe Aſperſions and Calumnies, which idle Ignorance hath caſt upon them of late.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Ingenuous Countrymen,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THe cauſe of my writing this following Diſcourſe was occaſioned by an accidental peruſal of a ſmall Pamphlet, entituled, <hi>A brief Declaration againſt Judicial Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy;</hi> the which doth ſeem to me to be done by one who hath ſold his <hi>Ingenuity</hi> to ſome Clergy-man for a reward, to ſpeak evil of that which he underſtands not: for had he known the ſubject againſt which he profeſſeth himſelf an enemy, he would have found better Arguments to have overthrown what he oppoſed. But ſeeing that the Author hath put himſelf upon the Stage, and become ſome Prieſts Champion, and hath proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Victory and Conqueſt over thoſe two excellent Arts of <hi>Magick</hi> and <hi>Astrology</hi> in his own conceit; yet for my own part I ſee nothing againſt them ſubſtantially, but a ſlender denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117775:6"/> of them, and then concluding them to be Diabolical, but nothing proved: Surely he wanted the Learning of ſome <hi>Chema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim Prieſt</hi> to have made good the Conqueſt. But ſeeing he is ſo valorous as to fight with his own ſhadow, mad man-like; for <hi>Magick</hi> and <hi>Astrology</hi> he never touched, becauſe they are both taken up too high for his ſquint-eyed reſpects to have the leaſt ſpeculation of.</p>
               <p>But now give me leave to declare my preſent Apprehenſion of <hi>Magick</hi> and <hi>Astrology,</hi> what they are, and what are the grounds of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What Magick is.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, for <hi>Magick</hi> (miſtake me not) I go not about to juſtifie all Arts, which are falſly called ſo; but for <hi>Magick</hi> it ſelf, which Art (ſaith <hi>Mirandula</hi>) few underſtand, and many repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend; as Dogs bark at thoſe they know not, ſo they hate and condemn the things they underſtand not: And it is too true, as one ſaith, that many men abhor the name and word <hi>(Magos)</hi> becauſe of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> who being not indeed <hi>Magus,</hi> but <hi>Goes</hi> (that is) familiar with evil ſpirits, uſurped that Title. For <hi>Magick, Conjuring,</hi> and <hi>Witchery,</hi> are far differing Arts, which <hi>Pliny</hi> being ignorant of, ſcoffed thereat: But <hi>Magus</hi> is a <hi>Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> word, whereby is expreſt ſuch a one as is altogether conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in divine things; And (as <hi>Plato</hi> affirmeth) that the Art of <hi>Magick</hi> is an Art of worſhiping of God. And ſometimes the word <hi>Magus</hi> is a Name of him that is a God by Nature, and ſometimes of him that is converſant in the ſervice and worſhip of God: in the latter ſence it is taken, <hi>Matth.</hi> 2.1. And this is the higheſt kinde, which <hi>Piccolominy</hi> called <hi>Divine Magick:</hi> and theſe are they that are called <hi>wiſe men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> For the fear and worſhip of God is the beginning of knowledg: And theſe are the men which the <hi>Greeks</hi> called <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> the <hi>Egyptians</hi> termed them <hi>Priests;</hi> with the <hi>Hebrews</hi> they were called <hi>Cabalists, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees;</hi> amongſt the <hi>Babylonians</hi> they were differenced by the names of <hi>Chaldeans:</hi> amongſt the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, Magicians:</hi> And therefore one ſpeaking of <hi>(Hoſtanes)</hi> one of the ancient <hi>Magicians,</hi> uſeth theſe words, <hi>He was one who
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117775:6"/> aſcribed the due Majeſty to the true God:</hi> He alſo hath delivered, <hi>that there are Devils earthly and wandering, and Enemies to Mankinde.</hi> So alſo the late Kings Father, in his Book of <hi>Daemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nology,</hi> confeſſeth, that in the <hi>Perſian</hi> Tongue the word <hi>(Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus)</hi> imports as much as <hi>a Contemplator of Divine and Heavenly Sciences:</hi> and he alſo avoweth, that under the name of <hi>Magick</hi> untruly all diabolical and wicked Arts are comprehended. And is it not ſo indeed, when thoſe that profeſs themſelves Practicioners in the <hi>Magick</hi> Art, as the Author of that ridiculous Pamphlet terms himſelf, ſhould not be able to diſtinguiſh betwixt that which is <hi>Magick</hi> truly, and what is falſly termed ſo? For that <hi>Magick</hi> which the late Kings Father did condemn, was that, wherein the Devil is a party, and not that lawful <hi>Magick</hi> which he juſtifies, the which he doth diſtinguiſh from <hi>Necromancy, Witchcraft,</hi> and the reſt; of all which he hath writ learnedly. So alſo we read in the ſecond of <hi>Daniel</hi> of four kindes of wiſe men, <hi>viz. Inchanters,</hi> and the <hi>Astrologians, Sorcerers,</hi> and <hi>Chalde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans:</hi> The firſt, according to the Opinion of ſome, were <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers,</hi> according to the Note of <hi>Vatablus,</hi> which is this, that the <hi>Magi</hi> are the ſame with the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> as the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> are with the <hi>Grecians,</hi> (that is to ſay) Men that profeſs the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of all things both divine and humane: And according to the Opinion of that worthy Gentleman Sir <hi>Walter Rawley,</hi> whoſe words are theſe; That the <hi>Greeks</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> call them <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanters; Junius, Magicians; Caſtalion, Conjecturers;</hi> and in the <hi>Syrian</hi> they are all four called by one name, <hi>viz. the wiſe men of Babel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond ſort <hi>Junius</hi> and our <hi>Engliſh</hi> call <hi>Aſtrologians; Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom</hi> and the <hi>Septuagint, Magicians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third kinde the <hi>Septuagint</hi> calls <hi>Witches</hi> or <hi>Poyſners,</hi> our Engliſh, <hi>Sorcerers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fourth ſort were <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> who profeſt themſelves to be able to foretell the Events of things, both Natural and Humane.</p>
               <p>There is a kinde of <hi>Magick,</hi> being part of <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> which hath reſpect to Sowing, and Planting, and all kindes of Husbandry, which is nothing elſe but the knowledg of the <hi>motions</hi> and <hi>influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences</hi> of the <hi>Stars</hi> in theſe lower <hi>Elements.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:117775:7"/>
               <p>And as <hi>Philo-Judaeus</hi> affirmeth, That by this part of <hi>Magick,</hi> or <hi>Astrology,</hi> together with the Motions of the Stars and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Bodies, <hi>Abraham</hi> found out the Knowledg of the true God, while he lived in <hi>Chaldae;</hi> And, as one ſaith, <hi>He knew the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator by his contemplating on the Creature.</hi> And <hi>Joſephus</hi> report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that <hi>Abraham</hi> taught the <hi>Egyptians</hi> firſt in the Art of <hi>Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy</hi> and <hi>Arithmetick,</hi> which before that, they had no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of them: And, according to the ſaying of another Author, that <hi>Abraham,</hi> the holieſt and wiſeſt of men, did firſt teach the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> then the <hi>Phoenicians,</hi> and laſtly the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Prieſts, <hi>Astrology</hi> and <hi>Divine Knowledg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But there is another kinde of <hi>Magick,</hi> which doth contain the whole <hi>Philoſophy of Nature,</hi> which is that which bringeth to light the hidden Vertues, and drawing them out of Natures Boſom, and converting them to humane uſes, by applying thoſe things that work to thoſe that ſuffer; and thus it is defined.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Definition of Magick.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MAgick</hi> is the Connexion of Natural Agents and Patients, anſwerable each to other, wrought by a wiſe man, to the bringing forth of ſuch or ſuch effects, as are wonderful to thoſe that know not their Cauſes.</p>
               <p>And this is that which hath layn under terms of Ignominy to this day: Ignorance producing Admiration, and Admiration Suſpicion, and then an undeſerved Cenſure paſt upon the work, or action, terming it to be Diabolical; and ſo attributing the ſecret workings, which the divine Wiſdom hath placed in the ſecret bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of Nature, to a Diabolical Power and Property, when it is nothing elſe but a mutual application of Natural Vertues, Agent and Suffering reciprocally: And thoſe that were converſant in this excellent Science in former times, were otherwiſe thought of, then now they are. For, as <hi>Pencer</hi> truly obſerveth, that the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi</hi> were the chief Miniſters of the <hi>Perſian</hi> Religion, as the <hi>Levites</hi> were amongſt Gods people, and they were given to the ſtudies of true <hi>Philoſophy:</hi> neither could any be Kings of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> who had not been firſt exerciſed in the myſteries and knowledg of the <hi>Magi.</hi> And this lawful <hi>Magick,</hi> which I do here ſpeak of, was
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117775:7"/> commended by <hi>Origen,</hi> that learned man, who doth moſt ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly declare, That it doth appertain to the practick part of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Philoſophy;</hi> teaching to work admirable things by the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual application of Natural Vertues. And <hi>Jerom,</hi> in his <hi>Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries</hi> upon <hi>Daniel,</hi> uſeth theſe words; But common cuſtom (ſaith he) taketh <hi>Magicians</hi> for <hi>Witches,</hi> who are otherwiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted in their own Nation, for they are the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> of the <hi>Chaldeans:</hi> yea Kings and Princes of that Nation do all that they do according to the knowledg of that Art: whence, at the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of the Lord our Saviour, they firſt of all underſtood his Birth; and coming unto <hi>Bethlehem</hi> did worſhip the Childe, the <hi>Star</hi> from above ſhewing him unto them.</p>
               <p>So it is clear, that there is a great deal of difference between the Doctrine of a <hi>Magician</hi> truly, and the abuſe of the word. But if you will beleeve the Author of that Pamphlet, he will tell you that he is a <hi>Magician</hi> in theſe our days, who having entered a combination with the Prince of Darkneſs, uſeth his help in any matter; but the Art of <hi>Magick</hi> is of the wiſdom of Nature: But as for other Arts, which have aſſumed the Title of <hi>Magick,</hi> they were invented by the ſubtilty and falſhood of the Devil; and in this there is none other Doctrine, then the uſe of certain Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies by an evil and wicked faith: in the other none evil, but the inveſtigation of thoſe admirable Vertues, and occult Properties, which that infinite Wiſdom hath beſtowed and given to his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and how fitly to apply thoſe things that are to work, to thoſe things that are to ſuffer. And thoſe men that were ſtudious in this Art were called the <hi>Magi,</hi> which (<hi>Peter Martyr</hi> ſaith) the Ancients underſtood to be <hi>good and wiſe men.</hi> And as <hi>Ficinus</hi> ſaith, O thou fearful one, why doubteſt thou to uſe the name of <hi>Magus,</hi> a name gracious in the <hi>Gospel,</hi> which doth not ſignifie a <hi>Witch,</hi> or a <hi>Conjurer,</hi> but a <hi>wiſe man,</hi> and a <hi>Prieſt?</hi> And what hath brought ſo much ſlander upon this excellent knowledg, but baſe and idle Ignorance, which indeed is the mother of Admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? But give me leave to go yet further: This Art doth not onely enable us in the true knowledg of thoſe ſecret Vertues which are wrapped up in the boſom of Nature, but it may in ſome meaſure bring us to the true knowledg of the <hi>Divinity of Christ:</hi> and to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117775:8"/> uſe <hi>Mirandula</hi>'s words; <hi>For by understanding</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt activity of Natural Agents, we are aſſiſted to know the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity of Chriſt; for otherwiſe, the terms and limits of Natural Power and Vertue not rightly underſtood, we muſt needs doubt whether thoſe very works which Chriſt did, may not be done by natural means; and therefore I ſay not heretically, nor ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, but moſt truly and catholiquely, that by ſuch</hi> Magick <hi>we are furthered in knowing the Divinity of Chriſt.</hi> And ſeeing the <hi>Jews,</hi> and other the Enemies of Chriſtian Religion, do impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently and impiouſly object, that thoſe Miracles which Chriſt wrought were not above Nature, but by the exquiſite knowledg thereof performed; and as that learned Doctor <hi>Staughton</hi> ſaith in a ſmall Treatiſe of his, that the <hi>Jews</hi> have a blaſphemous Fable, that our Saviour found out the right pronunciation of the Name of God, the <hi>Tetragrammaton,</hi> and that wrought all his Miracles. But <hi>Mirandula,</hi> a man for his years fuller of the knowledg of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, then any of theſe latter times, might with Reaſon avow, that the utmoſt limits of Natures works being known, that the works which Chriſt did (which no man could do) do manifeſtly declare of themſelves, that they were wrought by a Hand which held Nature herein but as a penſil, and by a Power infinitely Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme and Divine. But on the contrary, there may be many won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful effects brought to paſs, by the Magical operation of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Vertues, ſuch as may produce no ſmall admiration in thoſe that underſtand not the ſecret workings and products of thoſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues; for it is undoubtedly true, that all Secondary Cauſes do ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily work, and neceſſarily produce their proper effects, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of that Connexion that they have with the firſt Cauſe, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondency that they have to thoſe divine Patterns and eternal <hi>Idea's,</hi> whence every thing hath its determinate place in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitype, whence it lives and draws it original, and the vertue of all things, as of Stones, Herbs, Metals, living Creatures, and all which are from God are placed; who although he works by the Intelligences and Heavens upon theſe inferior things, yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times thoſe <hi>Media's</hi> being let alone, or their Miniſtry ſuſpended, the firſt Cauſe doth then work of it ſelf, which works are then call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Miracles:</hi> For whereas, by the command and order of the firſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117775:8"/> Cauſe, the ſecondary Cauſes (which <hi>Plato,</hi> and others, calls <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi>) do neceſſarily work, and neceſſarily produce their proper effects, yet ſometimes, according to the pleaſure of the firſt Cauſe, their Miniſtry is either ſuſpended, or finiſhed, that they wholly ceaſe from that neceſſary command and order; and theſe are the greateſt Miracles of God. So the Sun, at the requeſt of <hi>Joſuah,</hi> ſtood ſtill for the ſpace of a whole day. So, at the deſire of <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kias,</hi> it went back ten hours. So the fire in the <hi>Chaldean</hi> furnace did not conſume the <hi>three Children.</hi> So when that our Saviour Chriſt did ſuffer at a full Moon, the Sun was eclipſed.</p>
               <p>But if the Miniſtry of theſe ſecondary Cauſes be not ſuſpended or finiſhed, then they ſhew forth their proper powers and vertues, in their ſeveral effects, according to that order in the which the Wiſdom of the firſt Cauſe ordained them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What the Secondary Cauſes are.</head>
               <p>NOw if it be demanded, what theſe Secondary Cauſes are; I anſwer, They are all thoſe Miniſtring Powers, which God, the firſt Cauſe, hath ſet up under himſelf, for the regulating and governing of theſe inferior things; for there is not any thing to be found, which is not governed and ruled by theſe Miniſtring Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers under the firſt Cauſe. For God, the chief Cauſe, and Original of all Vertues, affords the Seal of the <hi>Idea's</hi> to the Intelligences, his Miniſters; who, like faithful Executors, do ſeal every thing committed to them, with the Ideal Vertue, by the Heavens and Stars, as it were Inſtruments in the mean time diſpoſing the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to receive thoſe forms which reſide in the divine Majeſty (as <hi>Plato</hi> ſaith) to be carryed down by the <hi>Stars;</hi> and the Giver of Forms diſtributeth them by the Miniſtry of <hi>Intelligences,</hi> which he hath appointed over his works, Governors and Keepers, unto whom this ability is entruſted in things committed to them, That every vertue of Stones, Herbs, Minerals, and all the reſt, might be from the <hi>Intelligences</hi> governing; therefore the form and vertue proceeds firſt from the <hi>Idea's,</hi> and after from the <hi>Intelligences</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning and ruling, and next from the Aſpects of the <hi>Stars</hi> diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and further from the diſpoſed Compliances of the Elements
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117775:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> anſwering to the Influences of the Heavens, by which the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> themſelves are diſpoſed; They have then ſuch <hi>operations</hi> in theſe inferior things, by the expreſs forms; but in the Heavens, by the <hi>vertues</hi> diſpoſing; in the <hi>Intelligences,</hi> by means mediating; in the <hi>Architype,</hi> by the <hi>Idea's,</hi> and exemplary forms: All which is neceſſary to meet in the effects of every thing, in the <hi>execution</hi> of the <hi>vertue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then it muſt needs be, that there is wonderful <hi>operation</hi> in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Herb</hi> and <hi>Stone,</hi> but greater in the <hi>Stars,</hi> beyond which every thing gets much to it ſelf by the <hi>Intelligence</hi> governing, but chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the higheſt cauſe, to which all things, being mutually finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, do correſpond, conſonant by its harmonial <hi>conſent,</hi> as it were with Hymns, praiſing together the higheſt workman.</p>
               <p>By the true knowledg of what hath been ſpoken, many and great things may be done, by the coupling and joyning of the <hi>Powers</hi> and <hi>Vertues</hi> of the Superiors with their <hi>Patients,</hi> the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriors agreeing and correſponding therewith.</p>
               <p>This is truly <hi>Magick,</hi> and a thing much to be honored and eſteemed; This is the moſt high and worthieſt Science in the World, lawful in all the parts of it, free from all evil encumbran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and diabolical practices, voyd of <hi>Superstition,</hi> a great means to attain the higheſt knowledg of that infinite Wiſdom and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, who hath created all things in order and form, and who ruleth in and over all things by his Miniſtring Powers, whom he hath ſet over all things in their ſeveral orders, for the <hi>diſtribution</hi> of his <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Vertue</hi> (as the firſt Original of all <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Vertue</hi>) to all things, according to the fore-decree of the firſt Cauſe, with a reſpect had to the <hi>matter</hi> receiving; and this <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</hi> hath a ſtedfaſt cauſe, not by chance or accident, but effectual and potent, and not failing, doing nothing in vain, nor fruitleſs; by it thoſe Powers exiſting in the nature of all things are moved, the which Powers are the <hi>operations</hi> of the <hi>Idea's,</hi> under the chief Cauſe, which do not err, but by the <hi>impurity</hi> and <hi>inequality</hi> of the <hi>matter:</hi> for celeſtial Influences may be hindered by the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and unfitneſs of the <hi>matter</hi> receiving, whence the <hi>Platonicks</hi> had that Proverb, <hi>That Celeſtial Vertues were infuſed, according to the deſert of the matter:</hi> Wherefore in thoſe things, in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117775:9"/> which theſe <hi>Celestial Powers</hi> and <hi>Virtues</hi> are leſs drowned and incumbered in the <hi>matter</hi> receiving, have more powerful <hi>operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and produce more admirable effects, when thoſe things are fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly collected, prepared, and duly applyed to their <hi>Patient,</hi> the which <hi>application</hi> ſtirs up that ſecret and hid <hi>virtue</hi> of the <hi>Agent,</hi> and produceth the like <hi>quality</hi> in the thing annexed. As for inſtance; <hi>Salt,</hi> the ſecret virtue of which lieth hid in it ſelf, until that there is annexed to it a reciprocal <hi>matter,</hi> which moves and ſtirs up that <hi>virtue,</hi> ſo that it is infuſed into the <hi>matter</hi> joyned to it, the which <hi>matter,</hi> according to the <hi>quality</hi> of its receivingneſs, is alſo able to infuſe the like property into other things joyned to it. So alſo the <hi>Load-ſtone</hi> doth infuſe its <hi>ſecret virtue</hi> into <hi>Iron,</hi> approaching near to it, and doth ſo faſten the <hi>virtue</hi> to the <hi>Iron,</hi> that it is able alſo to draw <hi>Iron</hi> to it ſelf, anſwerable to that power of <hi>Attracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> that it hath received from the <hi>Load-stone;</hi> and this ariſes from that reciprocal property which is in the <hi>matter</hi> affected, the which is wrought upon, and moved by the <hi>ſecret virtue</hi> of the <hi>Agent</hi> applyed. This alſo we find to be produced upon the Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, by the virtue and influence of the Superiors, for the Celeſtial Powers do work the like in Terreſtials; for we ſee that the <hi>Moon</hi> doth attract the vaſt body of the <hi>waters,</hi> ſo that they anſwer in their ebbings and flowings thoſe diverſity of Points that ſhe cuts in the Heavens in her <hi>Diurnal Motion.</hi> So likewiſe the <hi>Heliotro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium,</hi> that ſober Herb, who correſponds with the <hi>motion</hi> of the <hi>Sun</hi> by a <hi>ſecret virtue,</hi> which doth declare that there is ſomething of the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moons virtue</hi> infuſed, by the which they are wrought to ſuch obedience. Doth not the Marigold, and many other flowers, open their bloſſoms at the <hi>Suns</hi> riſing, as if they did rejoyce at his approach, and fold themſelves in, as if they mourned for his departure? All which is from that <hi>ſecret Agreement</hi> and Correſpondency of their <hi>virtues.</hi> For my own part, I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that all things that are under the Luner Globe in this infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior world, ſubject to <hi>generation</hi> and <hi>corruption,</hi> they are alſo in the Celeſtial world, but in a certain celeſtial manner; ſo alſo in the Intellectual world, but of a far more perfect and better ſtamp, and laſtly moſt perfect in the <hi>Architype:</hi> And in this order every thing below doth anſwer to its Superior, and by it to the higheſt,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117775:10"/> according to its proper kind, and doth receive <hi>virtue</hi> from them, from the <hi>Heavens</hi> indeed, that Celeſtial Force, which ſome call the <hi>Middle Nature,</hi> or <hi>the ſpirit of the world;</hi> and from the Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual world, that ſpiritual &amp; living Vapour, being every tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent virtue qualifying; and laſtly from the <hi>Architype,</hi> by theſe means between (according to its degree) the original force of all Perfection.</p>
               <p>Hence every thing may be fitly reduced, from theſe Inferiors to the <hi>Stars,</hi> from them to the <hi>Intelligences</hi> of the ſame, and from thence to the <hi>Architype,</hi> out of the order of which all <hi>Magick</hi> and <hi>ſecret Philoſophy</hi> doth flow; for dayly ſome <hi>natural thing</hi> is drawn by <hi>Art,</hi> and dayly ſome <hi>divine thing</hi> is drawn by <hi>Nature,</hi> which when ſome of the learned <hi>Egyptians</hi> did behold, they call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Nature</hi> it ſelf a <hi>Magician,</hi> that is to ſay, the Magical Force it ſelf, in the <hi>Attraction</hi> of the like by the like, and of things agreeing by things that agree; and the <hi>Greeks</hi> called ſuch <hi>Attractions,</hi> by the <hi>mutual Agreement</hi> of Superior with Inferior between them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>Sympathy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for inſtance: We know that in the <hi>El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ments, Water</hi> agrees with <hi>Earth</hi> in Coldneſs, <hi>Water</hi> with <hi>Ayr</hi> in Moiſtneſs, <hi>Ayr</hi> with <hi>Fire</hi> in Heat, <hi>Fire</hi> with the <hi>Heavens</hi> in the <hi>Materia.</hi> So <hi>Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals</hi> agree with <hi>Plants</hi> in their Unſenſibleneſs, <hi>Plants</hi> with <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals</hi> in Growing, <hi>Animals</hi> with <hi>Man</hi> in Sence, <hi>Man</hi> with <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> in Underſtanding, <hi>Angels</hi> with <hi>God</hi> in Immortality. So alſo <hi>Stones</hi> and <hi>Mettals</hi> agree with <hi>Plants, Plants</hi> with <hi>Animals, Animals</hi> with the <hi>Heavens,</hi> the <hi>Heavens</hi> with the <hi>Intelligences,</hi> and thoſe with the <hi>Divine Properties</hi> and <hi>Artributes,</hi> and with <hi>God</hi> himſelf. So the <hi>Divinity</hi> anſwers to the <hi>Mind,</hi> the <hi>Mind</hi> to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> to the <hi>Intentions,</hi> the <hi>Intentions</hi> to the <hi>Repreſentation,</hi> the <hi>Repreſentation</hi> to the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving</hi> it, the <hi>Receiving</hi> to the <hi>Senſes,</hi> and at laſt the <hi>Senſes</hi> to the <hi>thing</hi> it ſelf. For ſuch is the binding together and continuity of <hi>Nature,</hi> that that every Superior virtue doth diſperſe its beams through every Inferior thing, by a long and continued rank, flows even to the utmoſt: And the Inferiors do even reach to the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt by their ſeveral Superiors, for ſo the Inferiors are annexed to the Superiors by each other, that the Influence from the Head, the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117775:10"/> firſt Cauſe, as it were a certain Chain ſtretched out, proceedeth, even to the very Loweſt, wherefore if one be touched, it trembles or ſhakes wholy on the ſudden, and ſuch a touching ſounds even to the other end; and one Inferior being moved, the Superior is alſo moved, unto which that doth anſwer and correſpond: As the <hi>ſtring</hi> in any <hi>Instrument</hi> being touched, cauſes all the reſt to tremble.</p>
               <p>So it is manifeſt, that all Inferior things are under the Superiors, and after a manner (as ſaith <hi>Proclus</hi>) are within each other, to wit, the Higheſt in the Loweſt, and the Loweſt in the Higheſt: ſo earthly things are in Heaven, but as in a celeſtial cauſe and manner; and the Celeſtial are in Earth, but after an earthly manner, to wit, according to the effect. So we ſay that here are ſome things <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,</hi> and ſome things <hi>Lunar,</hi> in which the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon</hi> doth cauſe ſomewhat of their <hi>virtue,</hi> whence ſuch like things do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive very many <hi>operations</hi> and <hi>properties,</hi> agreeable to the <hi>operations</hi> and <hi>properties</hi> of the <hi>Stars</hi> and <hi>Signs</hi> under which they are.</p>
               <p>So it is manifeſtly known to all <hi>Naturaliſts</hi> and <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> that <hi>ſober things</hi> have <hi>relation</hi> to the <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Heart,</hi> becauſe of <hi>Leo</hi> the Houſe of the <hi>Sun,</hi> and <hi>Aries</hi> his <hi>Exaltation;</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Mars</hi> have <hi>relation</hi> to the <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Privy parts,</hi> becauſe of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> and <hi>Scorpio,</hi> the two Houſes of <hi>Mars,</hi> and ſo of the reſt. So you ſee that all <hi>Inferior virtues</hi> do correſpond with their <hi>Celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,</hi> the <hi>Celeſtial</hi> with their <hi>Intellectual,</hi> and the <hi>Intellectual</hi> with the <hi>Ideal</hi> and <hi>Architypical,</hi> or <hi>firſt Cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So the <hi>Elements</hi> are to be found in all things, but differently; for in theſe Inferior but muddy and thick, but in the Celeſtial more pure and bright, in the Super-celeſtial living and bleſſed every ways: The <hi>Elements</hi> are therefore the <hi>Ideas</hi> of things to be produced, in the <hi>Intelligences</hi> as <hi>Powers</hi> deſtributed, in the <hi>Heavens</hi> as <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,</hi> in theſe <hi>Inferior things as thicker Forms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So the <hi>Light,</hi> a very <hi>formal Quality,</hi> and a <hi>ſimple Act,</hi> and Image of an <hi>Intelligence</hi> (or <hi>Spirit,</hi>) firſt is diffuſed into all things by the <hi>divine Mind:</hi> but in <hi>God</hi> himſelf the <hi>Father,</hi> who is the <hi>Father of Lights,</hi> it is the <hi>firſt and true Light;</hi> and afterward in the <hi>Son,</hi> the enlightening and abounding <hi>Brightneſs</hi> of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:117775:11"/> in the <hi>Spirit</hi> a <hi>burning Fulger,</hi> exceeding even the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the <hi>Seraphins</hi> (as <hi>Dionyſius</hi> ſaith,) being diffuſed in the <hi>Angels,</hi> it becomes a <hi>ſhining underſtanding,</hi> and a <hi>Joy</hi> ſhed forth above the bounds of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> yet received by divers degrees, according to the Nature of the <hi>Intelligence</hi> receiving; afterward it deſcends into the <hi>celeſtial things,</hi> where it is made a <hi>plenty</hi> of <hi>life,</hi> and an <hi>effectual Propogation,</hi> and alſo a <hi>viſible Brightneſs,</hi> and in the <hi>Fire</hi> a certain <hi>natural force</hi> imprinted by the <hi>Celeſtials:</hi> Laſtly, in <hi>Man</hi> it is made a <hi>bright diſcourſe of Reaſon,</hi> and the <hi>knowledg of divine things,</hi> and wholy <hi>rational:</hi> And this alſo is manifeſt by the <hi>dispoſition</hi> of the <hi>body,</hi> as the <hi>Peripateticks</hi> will have it, or which I conceive is more true, according to the pleaſure of the Cauſe giving, which diſtributes to every one according to his Will, from thence it paſſeth the <hi>fancy,</hi> and as yet it is above the <hi>ſenſes,</hi> and being only made imagineable, at length it attains to the <hi>ſenſes,</hi> and eſpecially to that of the <hi>eyes,</hi> in that it is made a <hi>viſible clearneſs,</hi> and is ſtretched forth in each of theſe proſpicious bodies, in which it becomes a <hi>colour,</hi> and a <hi>ſhining fireneſs;</hi> in <hi>dark things</hi> it becomes a helpful <hi>ingendering virtue,</hi> and pierceth even unto the <hi>center,</hi> where the <hi>beams</hi> being collected into a <hi>narrow ſpace,</hi> it becomes a <hi>dark heat,</hi> tormenting and boyling.</p>
               <p>So all feel the force of <hi>Light</hi> according to their <hi>capacity,</hi> which joyning all things to it ſelf by a <hi>quickening heat,</hi> and going through all things that have Being, brings forth their <hi>qualities</hi> and <hi>vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues</hi> through every thing.</p>
               <p>So you ſee that all <hi>Inferior things</hi> are in the <hi>Superior,</hi> but more clear and perfect then here below; ſo all <hi>Superior virtues</hi> are to be found in the <hi>Inferiors,</hi> more or leſs anſwerable to the <hi>capacity</hi> of the <hi>Receiver,</hi> but more groſs and muddy, and not ſo powerful and operative as in their Superiors. For we ſee by experience, that all <hi>Medicines</hi> are compoſed of ſeveral <hi>ingrediencies,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>imperfection</hi> of the <hi>virtue</hi> of one <hi>material</hi> in its <hi>operation,</hi> and therefore they ſtrengthen that imperfect <hi>property</hi> by addition of others of the like kind, that ſo they might produce thoſe <hi>proper effects</hi> propoſed by the <hi>Arts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ingenuous Reader, I hope by this that <hi>Magick</hi> is no ſuch Art as the moſt of men ignorantly take it to be, nor as the Author of that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117775:11"/> Pamplet is pleaſed to eſteem of it; for had it been ſo, certainly it would have been reproved in <hi>Solomon,</hi> the wiſeſt of men, who without doubt was excellently acquainted with this <hi>Mystery;</hi> for his knowledg in <hi>Nature</hi> was ſuch, and ſo perfect, that he knew and underſtood the <hi>virtues</hi> and <hi>properties</hi> of all <hi>Trees, Plants, Beaſts, Fowls,</hi> and <hi>Fiſhes,</hi> with their <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Seaſons;</hi> he alſo declared their <hi>virtues</hi> and <hi>uſes</hi> in the curing of <hi>Diſeaſes,</hi> (as <hi>Sui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> reports,) whoſe words are to this effect, <hi>That Solomon wrote of the Remedy of all Diſeaſes, and graved the ſame upon the ſides of the Porch of the Temple, which Ezekias pulled down,</hi> as the ſame Author ſaith. Nay <hi>Joſephus</hi> goeth farther, and ſaith, that wrote Books of <hi>Invocations</hi> and <hi>Inchantments</hi> to cure <hi>Diſeaſes,</hi> and to expel <hi>evil Spirits,</hi> he alſo ſpeaketh of one <hi>Eliazarus,</hi> who by the Root in <hi>Solomas</hi> Ring, diſpoſſeſſed divers perſons of <hi>evil Spirits</hi> in the preſence of <hi>Vespaſian,</hi> and many others. So alſo <hi>Moſes,</hi> the <hi>Law-giver</hi> and <hi>Prince</hi> of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> endued with <hi>Magick</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> is read in <hi>Joſephus</hi> to have made <hi>Rings of Love</hi> and <hi>Forgetfulneſs:</hi> This I am really perſwaded, that <hi>Moſes</hi> was very knowing in all the <hi>ſecrets</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> or as one ſaith, a man that was the moſt excellently learned in all <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Humane Knowledg;</hi> and for ought as I do know, was as able to have brought forth the <hi>Products</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> in as admirable a way, as did the <hi>Magicians</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> before <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> for I conceive that he was as knowing in the <hi>ſecret</hi> and <hi>occult workings</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> as they: And whereas it is a received Opinion of many, That thoſe <hi>Frogs</hi> which the <hi>Magicians</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> did produce were but falſe Semblences; my opinion is otherwiſe: for I am really convinced, that <hi>Moſes,</hi> that man ſent and impowered of God for ſo eminent a work, could not be deceived with ſuch falſe Appearances. But I ſhall adhere to the Judgment of that learned <hi>Pariſienſes,</hi> who ſaith, That in ſuch works the ſudden <hi>generation</hi> of <hi>Frogs, Lice,</hi> and <hi>Worms,</hi> and ſome other <hi>creatures,</hi> in all which <hi>Nature</hi> alone worketh, but by means ſtrengthening the ſeeds of <hi>Natur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and quickning them in ſuch wiſe, that they ſo haſten the work of <hi>gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> that it ſeemeth not to be the work of <hi>nature</hi> to the ignorant which uſually worketh more ſlowly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but they think it to be done by the power of <hi>Devils;</hi> but they who are learned in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:117775:12"/> marvel not at ſuch workings, but glorifie the Creator. Many the like things may and have been done by no unjuſt way or means, but wholy by the more <hi>ſecret</hi> and <hi>occult workings</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> which to thoſe that apprehend not the way of <hi>operation,</hi> have had a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of a <hi>Diabolical Agent;</hi> but their <hi>ignorance</hi> hath miſled them, as it doth many at this day: And I were able to deliver the <hi>Precepts</hi> of ſome learned men for Inſtances, but it may ſuffice that I have cleared the <hi>ſubstantial Grounds</hi> of <hi>Magick,</hi> and have vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated that <hi>excellent Art</hi> from thoſe groſs <hi>Calumnies</hi> and <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſions</hi> that have been laid upon it, either by men wholy ignorant in it, or ſuch who have received a prejudice againſt it, to both, I ſay, that they may as well aſperſe the <hi>Magical Policy</hi> of <hi>Jacob,</hi> in cauſing the <hi>ſtrongeſt Cattel</hi> of <hi>Laban</hi> to bring forth <hi>ſpotted young ones,</hi> by his laying of <hi>ſpotted Rods</hi> in the <hi>watering-troughs</hi> and <hi>gutters,</hi> where the <hi>female Cattel</hi> coming to drink, at what time they had coupled with the <hi>male,</hi> that they then ſeeing the Rods might conceive <hi>ſpotted young ones,</hi> the which ſight wrought ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon, and powerfully affected the conceiving and forming facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Cattel,</hi> and ſo did enſtamp the like colours upon the thing conceived, for that part of the ſeed which maketh it fruitful, to wit, the <hi>ſpirits</hi> which wander all over the <hi>body,</hi> theſe containing the <hi>Idea</hi> or form of the particular parts to be formed, being <hi>ayr</hi> and <hi>moiſt,</hi> are ready to receive any impreſſion, which is conveyed in at the eye, and doth frame the thing anſwerable in ſome ſort to the thing received: As I have read of a <hi>Negor</hi> woman, that conceived a beautiful <hi>white child</hi> by the help of her Imagination, it being fixed upon a <hi>beautiful picture</hi> in the Act of <hi>Generation,</hi> which is wrought by nothing elſe but that reciprocal <hi>quality,</hi> and tender <hi>property</hi> of thoſe <hi>ayral</hi> and <hi>moiſt ſpirits</hi> which are in every ſeed in <hi>conception.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My requeſt therefore is, that all ingenuous men would ſeriouſly ſtudy and contemplate the <hi>creature,</hi> and thoſe excellencies that God, the firſt Cauſe and Original of all things, hath put into <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> which doth very much ſpeak out the <hi>infinite Wiſdom, Power, Goodneſs, Love,</hi> and <hi>Kindneſs</hi> of him who doth all in all, by theſe <hi>miniſtring Powers</hi> that he in his Wiſdom hath ſet up over all theſe <hi>inferior things</hi> for the ſhewing forth of theſe received <hi>virtues,</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:117775:12"/> which doth flow down from the firſt and chief <hi>Good</hi> into all <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> more or leſs, anſwerable to the good pleaſure of the firſt Cauſe or Giver, and according to the fitneſs of the Receiver, for there is not any thing to be found which hath not ſomething of this good infuſed into it, which <hi>Virgil</hi> had a ſight of when he ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered theſe words, <hi>There is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a Fire force, and a Celeſtial Originial to theſe ſeeds, as far as the Noxious Bodies do not hinder.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this is all that I ſhall ſpeak concerning the Art of <hi>Magick;</hi> more I could have ſaid, but this ſhall ſuffice, as an <hi>Anſwer</hi> to that <hi>Book,</hi> in reference to that <hi>ſecret Myſtery,</hi> which I hope will ſatisfie the Ingenuous Reader.</p>
               <p>I ſhall now ſpeak briefly to the other Art, <hi>viz.</hi> that of <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> which the Author of that Pamplet is pleaſed to ſtigmatiſe with the like ignominious Terms as he hath done that moſt profound Art of <hi>Magick,</hi> before ſpoken of, and I hope to any ingenuous and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial man cleared and vindicated by the foregoing Diſcourſe: It remaineth now for me to clear this of <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> which I ſhall, ſo far as I have received the knowledg thereof from the firſt Cauſe, who is the Giver of every good knowledg.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Aſtrology Defined.</head>
               <p>AS for <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> I conceive it to be an Art, by the which the <hi>influence</hi> and <hi>virtual operations</hi> of the <hi>ſuperior Bodies</hi> with their <hi>effects</hi> and <hi>ſignifications</hi> are brought to <hi>light</hi> and <hi>knowledg:</hi> I ſay, it is an Art by the which we come to know what the <hi>ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> and <hi>effects</hi> of the ſeveral <hi>Motions, Aspects,</hi> and <hi>Poſitions</hi> of the <hi>Heavenly Bodies</hi> do hint out unto us in reference to the <hi>World</hi> in general, and to <hi>Kingdoms, States, Cities, Families,</hi> and the <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular fate</hi> (if I may ſo call it) of <hi>every man</hi> and <hi>woman,</hi> with their ſeveral <hi>relations, conditions, dependance,</hi> and <hi>ends</hi> whatſoever, and that by the <hi>Heavens</hi> and <hi>Celeſtial Bodies:</hi> Now that the Celeſtial Bodies have an influence upon theſe Inferior Bodies here below, is already cleared in the foregoing Diſcourſe, the which I think no ingenuous man will deny; but that they have a <hi>relation</hi> to the <hi>Manifeſtation</hi> of the <hi>particular fare</hi> of every <hi>particular
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117775:13"/> Kingdom, State, Cities, Families</hi> and <hi>Perſons,</hi> is the thing to be cleared, which I ſhall do according to that knowledg that I have, which is not ſo perfect as I could deſire, or as I covet after.</p>
               <p>But that they have an Influence and Power over <hi>Kingdoms</hi> and <hi>States,</hi> in reference to their <hi>particular fates</hi> and <hi>changes,</hi> with the <hi>Manifeſtation</hi> thereof, it is moſt clear, and that from thoſe many and ſeveral <hi>Experiments</hi> that we have ſeen of late years in thoſe ſtrange and unexpected <hi>Cataſtrophe's</hi> of this <hi>Iſland,</hi> and they all or moſt made out conſpicuouſly, before they did come to paſs, by that worthy Gentleman Mr <hi>Lilly,</hi> (one whom I much honour for his love to his Country-men, in reſtoring of this <hi>Art,</hi> which was almoſt loſt, not only here, but almoſt all <hi>Europe</hi> over, whoſe learned Works, I muſt freely acknowledg, were the firſt grounds and cauſe of my <hi>preſent attainments,</hi>) and others, who was and are conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in the <hi>ſtudy</hi> of this <hi>excellent Art;</hi> witneſs thoſe ſeveral Books of theirs now extent, which contains nothing elſe but <hi>Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticks</hi> or <hi>Prophecies</hi> of <hi>future events,</hi> that were to be brought to paſs in their fit ſeaſons by means of the Superiors, who are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but <hi>miniſtring Powers</hi> appointed to diſperſe or carry down thoſe <hi>determinations</hi> of the firſt Cauſe, committed unto them by the <hi>Intelligences</hi> ruling, and this is that orderly way by which the chief Good brings all things to paſs in <hi>Nature</hi> in this inferior world, except thoſe immediate Acts, in which all theſe <hi>Mediums</hi> are ſuſpended, and the firſt Cauſe works of himſelf, and theſe Works are called by us <hi>Miracles,</hi> becauſe there is nothing of <hi>Nature</hi> found to co-operate in the work, or in that the <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> of all things doth not work in and by theſe means mediating: But when theſe <hi>Mediums</hi> have received thoſe <hi>patterns</hi> of work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then they ſhew forth the <hi>Intentions</hi> and <hi>Decrees</hi> of the firſt Cauſe, either by the ordinary <hi>Motion, Aspects</hi> and <hi>Poſition</hi> of the Celeſtial Bodies, which is the common courſe of the firſt Cauſe in <hi>Nature,</hi> or elſe in a more extraordinary way, as by unuſual <hi>Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritions,</hi> as of <hi>Comets</hi> or <hi>Blazing Star, three Suns, Men</hi> and <hi>Horſes</hi> in armour in a hoſtile manner fighting, <hi>Balls</hi> of <hi>Fire, Swords, Spears,</hi> and other weapons of <hi>war, forms</hi> of <hi>monſtrous Men</hi> and <hi>Beaſts,</hi> and many other ways, too tedious to be here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominated, all which are the Works of the <hi>Intelligential Angels,</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:117775:13"/> which are the fore-runners of ſome ſtrange Accidents or Change to befall the World in general, or ſome <hi>Kingdom, State, Cities, Families,</hi> or <hi>Perſons,</hi> who had their firſt beginnings under ſuch or ſuch a <hi>determinate Horoſcope,</hi> and <hi>Celeſtial Conſtellation,</hi> who with their beginnings receive a wonderful <hi>virtue</hi> of working or ſuffering, yea in ſuch a manner, that it becomes obedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt to that power ruling it in the Heavens, as our bodies are obedient to our Souls; ſo that when the Celeſtial Bodies are moved to any Change or Variation, then are thoſe things which are ſubject to that or that Celeſtial Body or Conſtellation moved and changed anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. Now this intenſive work or change which is determined in the firſt Cauſe, is made manifeſt in the Heavens ſome ſpace of time more or leſs before it is brought to paſs upon theſe Inferiors here below; ſo that thoſe that are learned in the Liberary of Heaven, ſees before-hand what is like to come to paſs upon ſuch or ſuch a <hi>Kingdom, State, Family,</hi> or <hi>perſons.</hi> Now for him that is verſed in the knowledg of their Effects, to declare what the <hi>intention</hi> of the firſt Cauſe is in reference to any of theſe particular ones, ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccounted and termed a <hi>Conjurer, Witch,</hi> and the like, what do they but as much as in them is, to ſtigmatiſe the ſecondary Cauſes, who are ſervants to the firſt Cauſe, to wit, God, who hath made and framed them by his unſpeakable Wiſdom in ſuch a <hi>ſeries</hi> and order of correſpondency, that they anſwer to all things more or leſs here below, as they agree with the <hi>Intelligences</hi> and <hi>Idea's</hi> of all things above; ſo that they do neceſſarily work, and ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily produce their proper effects, upon thoſe things that they govern in this inferior world, either to <hi>love</hi> and <hi>concord,</hi> or to <hi>ſtrife</hi> and <hi>enmity,</hi> which we call <hi>good</hi> and <hi>evil:</hi> and the cauſe why they operate not ſo ſtrongly and effectually, is becauſe of the <hi>unequality</hi> of the <hi>matter;</hi> for in ſuch things in which the ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or hath not that Rule and Domination as in others, in thoſe they work more ſlowly and imperfect, which is not becauſe of the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ability</hi> of their influence and virtue, but becauſe of the <hi>unſuitabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of the Subject; for they rule in ſome things more, in others leſs, yet they produce their effects in all, ſuitable to the correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of the <hi>matter</hi> with them; ſo that there is nothing in the inferior world, which is not more or leſs agreeing with theſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117775:14"/> Celeſtial Influences, and Heavenly Virtues.</p>
               <p>But now I ſhall deſcend to Particulars, as to declare the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Effects of the ſuperior Influences upon particular ones. But firſt, That they have relation to the World in general, take but that one Inſtance of <hi>Petrus de Aliaco</hi> concerning the Univerſal Flood, who quoting <hi>Albumazer,</hi> who did by <hi>Calculation</hi> of the <hi>Motions</hi> of the two <hi>ſuperior Planets,</hi> to wit, <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> did find that they did come to Conjunction in <hi>Cancer,</hi> a watery Sign, and in the fourth Houſe of Heaven, the which Sign was (as the ſame Author doth affirm) the Horoſcope of the Heavens firſt motion, <hi>viz.</hi> when the <hi>Creation</hi> was finiſhed, and all Celeſtial bodies had received their power of <hi>motion,</hi> in the which they were to continue, for the product of thoſe determinate effects upon the world, according to the <hi>intention</hi> of the firſt Cauſe. In this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Inſtance a curious eye may ſee much; by the which Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction (as ſome learned Authors doth aver) that that juſt man <hi>Noah</hi> had the fore-knowledg of the general Deluge: For, as the ſaid <hi>Aliaco</hi> confirmeth, that although <hi>Noah</hi> did well know the Flood by <hi>divine Revelation,</hi> yet this Conjunction being notorious, he could not be ignorant of the ſecond Cauſes from the firſt Cauſe, for that was not only a Sign, but a working Cauſe, by its power received from the firſt Cauſe, which is God himſelf; and alſo that by <hi>the windows of Heaven, Moſes</hi> meant this <hi>watery Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> The Authors words are theſe; <hi>It pleaſed God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to ordain by the courſe of the Heavens ſuch a Conſtellation, by the which all men might ſee therein their own destruction coming, and ſo forſake thoſe wicked ways wherein they walked, and call upon God for mercy.</hi> And of the ſame Judgment was the learned <hi>Pariſienſis,</hi> who underſtood that by <hi>the windows of Heaven</hi> were meant the <hi>great Conjunction</hi> of thoſe two <hi>ſuperior Planets,</hi> or theſe <hi>watery Conſtellations, Cancer, Piſces, Pleiades, Hyades,</hi> and <hi>Orion;</hi> and of the <hi>Planets, Venus</hi> and the <hi>Moon,</hi> which are the forcible Cauſes of the <hi>greatest Inundations:</hi> His own words are theſe; <hi>I perceive not what the Prophet of the</hi> Hebrews <hi>meaneth by theſe words,</hi> the windows of Heaven, <hi>unleſs he meaneth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thoſe Celeſtial Powers, by whoſe influence are engendered the Rain, and Inundations of Waters, ſuch as are the water Signs of</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:117775:14"/> Cancer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The which Conjunction happened (according to the opinion of <hi>Albumazur</hi>) 279 years, 248 days, and 9 hours before that it did ſhew its effects upon the inferior world: And thus it pleaſed God, that in the Courſe of his unſearchable Wiſdom, that this Conjunction ſhould be at ſuch a time, by which means there was <hi>vigour</hi> and <hi>faculty</hi> added for the <hi>operation</hi> of every <hi>vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,</hi> by which <hi>violent Eruptions</hi> of <hi>Springs</hi> and <hi>Fountains</hi> was cauſed from the abundance of the <hi>treaſure</hi> of their <hi>waters,</hi> taking <hi>retention</hi> from the <hi>Clouds,</hi> and condenſing <hi>ayr</hi> into <hi>water,</hi> a change familiar in theſe <hi>Elements,</hi> by the Miniſtry of his Angels, the which is the ordinary way of the firſt Cauſe, for the producing of his <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations</hi> upon the inferior world; I mean, by ſuch ſecondary Cauſes, as was the Conjunction of theſe two ſuperior <hi>Planets, viz. Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> the effects of which reſulted into that Univerſal Deluge, or general overflowing of the whole Earth with the <hi>Element</hi> of <hi>Water.</hi> But this ſhall ſuffice for the due proof of the firſt particular, to wit, That the Celeſtial Bodies have an Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon the World, for the producing of ſtrange effects, as they are Inſtruments under the firſt Cauſe, and alſo they are as to us Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtations before-had of their Events.</p>
               <p>But now I ſhall proceed to the ſecond particular, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Heavenly Bodies have an Influence upon <hi>Kingdoms</hi> and <hi>States,</hi> and that to the <hi>manifeſtation</hi> of their <hi>particular fates</hi> or <hi>changes,</hi> the which we have found by Experience of late years in this Iſland, verified to the purpoſe, and not only this, but that of <hi>Ireland,</hi> all or moſt of them made out before by M. <hi>Lilly,</hi> and others, and by none other way or means but by the Art of <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> by the which they have to the purpoſe declared the Events and Effects of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Bodies in their Influence, and in what particulars they would manifeſt themſelves. But for the better clearing of this particular, I ſhall give you one or two <hi>ancient Preſidents,</hi> long ago brought to paſs: As for inſtance, That <hi>Star</hi> which ſuddenly appeared in the time of <hi>Hipparchus,</hi> which ſignified the transferring of the <hi>Greekiſh Empire</hi> into the hands of the <hi>Romans,</hi> which was not effected till 63 years after, which begun about 42 years before Chriſt. Did not the Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> in the year 1425. which were in <hi>Scorpio,</hi> a treacherous and falſe Sign, find
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117775:15"/> us in <hi>England</hi> engaged in a War with <hi>France, Spain</hi> at the ſame time in diviſion about a Succeſſor in the Royal Power, and under the effects of the ſame Conjunction <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth was crowned at <hi>Paris?</hi> Alſo under the Conjunction of the two Superiors in the year 1603. in the Sign of <hi>Sagitarius,</hi> did not <hi>James</hi> King of <hi>Scotland</hi> come to be King of <hi>England?</hi> And as Mr <hi>Lilly</hi> ſaith in that unparalled Piece, <hi>viz. Englands Prophetical Merlin,</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Conjunction, uſeth theſe words, <hi>Could a more memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thing be in this world, then for a Scottiſh King to become Monarch of the Engliſh, and that without blows, conſidering the former Antipathy betwixt both Nations? Was not this in effect a new Monarchy, yea and a great one, to be King of England, Scotland, and Ireland?</hi> And hath not <hi>Ireland</hi> ſuffered to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe under the effects of theſe two <hi>Lunar Eclipſes,</hi> which was <hi>total,</hi> which happened the laſt year in the <hi>Constellations</hi> of <hi>Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> and <hi>Scorpio;</hi> the one being Conjunction with that kingly <hi>Star</hi> of the firſt <hi>Magnitude,</hi> called <hi>Aldeberion,</hi> or <hi>the Bulls eye,</hi> of the nature of <hi>Mars;</hi> the other in the <hi>Conſtellation</hi> of <hi>Scorpio,</hi> a moſt viporous Sign, with fixed ſtars of the nature of <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Saturn,</hi> whoſe effects did and doth ſtill ſhew themſelves power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully upon that deplorable Iſland, to the great deſtruction of her <hi>Natives;</hi> all which might have been fore-ſeen by thoſe that are converſant in contemplating of the Heavens, and yet by no combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation with the Powers that rule in the dark World. And was not that <hi>Comet</hi> which appeared in the year 1618. a fore-runner of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Changes</hi> and <hi>Mutations</hi> almoſt all <hi>Europe</hi> over? And I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that <hi>Scotland</hi> hath no cauſe to boaſt of the Effects of the Conjunction of the two <hi>malevolent Planets,</hi> viz. <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>July</hi> laſt. They who are deſirous to view things of this nature, if their own prejudice doth not detain them, they may read thoſe two Books of Mr <hi>Lilly</hi>'s, viz. <hi>Englands Prophetical Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> and <hi>The Worlds Catastrophe,</hi> the firſt publiſhed in 1644. the other in 1647. the which will produce variety of Preſidents of this nature, the which are things of that excellency and worth, that to an ingenuous man never the like were extent in <hi>Europe.</hi> I could be more large in this particular, but this I hope will ſatisfie the wiſe, for others I matter not, whoſe <hi>ſtupidity</hi> all the <hi>Preſidents</hi> in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117775:15"/> the world is not able to convince.</p>
               <p>But now I ſhall deſcend to the third particular, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Heavenly Bodies have an Influence upon <hi>particular Cities,</hi> and do ſhew forth ſome ſtrange <hi>Change</hi> or <hi>Mutation</hi> in their <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Laws, Cuſtoms, Liberties, Loſs,</hi> and <hi>Profit,</hi> which are all made out before conſpicuouſly by the ſuperior Bodies, according to the <hi>determination</hi> of the firſt Cauſe, by whoſe goodneſs all <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> flouriſh, and by whoſe will they again decline in their glory and pomp, and then fall into ſlavery and deſtruction: ſo it is no wonder if <hi>Monarchies, Kingdoms</hi> and <hi>Cities</hi> do change their manner of <hi>Government,</hi> and as it were a thing forſaken of its <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidential Angel,</hi> flying to another nature of other power; and ſo always <hi>Kingdoms</hi> and <hi>Cities,</hi> when they have attained to the height of their glory, they then decline, and become worſe and worſe both in their <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Cuſtoms,</hi> and by that means the conditions of men become contrary, ſo that a <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>hatred</hi> and <hi>ſedition</hi> is generated, which produces ruine and deſtruction, or a transferring of the <hi>Government</hi> thereof unto ſtrangers; as was that moſt magnificent and glorious <hi>City</hi> of <hi>Constantinople</hi> from under the <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> now become the <hi>Seat Royal</hi> of the <hi>Paganiſh Mahomitan,</hi> which was effected under the Influence of the Conjunction of the two Superiors in <hi>Cancer,</hi> in the year 1444. whoſe Aſcendant is <hi>Cancer,</hi> the Sign of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, whoſe <hi>Chriſtian Beauty</hi> then declined into a <hi>Paganiſh Deformity:</hi> And did not the ſame Conjunction produce a vaſt loſs to the <hi>Venicians,</hi> by an Inundation of the Sea, to the value of a Million of money, whoſe Aſcendant is that watery Sign of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer?</hi> And I believe that <hi>London</hi> hath no cauſe to boaſt of its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit that it hath received from the effects of the laſt Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> in the year 1642. which was in <hi>Piſces,</hi> which beholds the Aſcendant of <hi>London</hi> with a hateful Square; and was not <hi>Mercury</hi> the Lord thereof under the Sun beams, and aſpected by the Moon with a Square? Arguments of no good to redound to it: Neither will the ſlow <hi>motion</hi> of <hi>malicious Saturn</hi> through the <hi>Conſtellation</hi> of the Twins, with the Conjunction of <hi>angry Mars,</hi> which was in <hi>July</hi> laſt, produce any cauſe of boaſting to the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> either in their Civil Power or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117775:16"/> the which ſome ſpace of time may and will make manifeſt, though not to the conviction of their <hi>ſelfiſh Opinions,</hi> yet will prove fatal I fear to their Trade and Commerce, the which the <hi>declination</hi> of their <hi>Eſtates</hi> will teſtifie: And I wiſh, O <hi>London,</hi> that thou mayſt not feel the effects thereof alſo in thy <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> whoſe Glory exceeds almoſt all the <hi>Cities</hi> in <hi>Europe:</hi> May not the time be, and that ſhortly, that thy pomp and beauty in thy <hi>Societies</hi> may be eclipſed? I wiſh it may not, yet I profeſs I fear it: But no more of that. Have we not had a clear demonſtration of the fading glory of the Royal Power in this Kingdom of late, which was hinted, nay clearly manifeſted, before-hand in the laſt Conjunction of the Superiors in <hi>Piſces,</hi> which beheld the Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant of our <hi>Engliſh Monarchy</hi> with a <hi>hateful oppoſition,</hi> and what the product thereof hath been, and is like to be, let the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial judg; and not only that Conjunction of the Superiors, but all thoſe <hi>eminent Configurations</hi> of late years have manifeſted the ſame: but more eſpecially that ſtrange <hi>Apperition</hi> of <hi>three Suns</hi> in <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1648. which were ſeen viſibly to divers in <hi>London,</hi> and near adjacent, which were the Meſſengers of a final Period to that Houſe, in reſpect of the Regal Power, which were the Works of the Intelligencial Angels, who were willing to communicate the Decree of the <hi>great Creator,</hi> which was to be effected in a ſmall ſpace of time here below, though conceived long before in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of the firſt Cauſe, as all things of the like nature are. And ſhall God be ſo willing to ſuffer nothing to come to paſs, or be effected in this lower world, but doth give unto us firſt Celeſtial Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his <hi>Intentions</hi> and <hi>Determinations,</hi> and ſhall we call ſuch as are converſant in the <hi>contemplation</hi> of thoſe Wonders and My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, <hi>Witches, Conjurers,</hi> and the like? O <hi>ingratitude,</hi> not to be parallel'd! Which of you all who are ſo ſottiſh as to abuſe the <hi>Students</hi> in this lawful Art, that would reject the counſel of the meaneſt man who adviſeth you of an apparant danger, which is ready for to ſeize upon you, and declares the prevention by certain means? If you reject it, worſe then mad men: Will you reject and ſlight the <hi>Prognoſticks</hi> of able <hi>Artists?</hi> Look to it in time, leſt you be branded for your folly in future Ages: For had his late <hi>Majesty,</hi> and ſome great men, really conſidered the <hi>Prophecies</hi> of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117775:16"/> ſome <hi>Engliſh Artists,</hi> it had been otherwiſe with then it was. I will give you the <hi>Paradoxial Prophecy</hi> of that able Artiſt Mr <hi>Lilly</hi> in <hi>Merlin,</hi> pag. 110. <hi>Wo to a great Family of Europe, that was, is now, but ſhall be no more; it's not old, it's not ancient, like an untimely birth it's cut off, and ſhall never again flouriſh either in Branch or Root, &amp;c.</hi> Lord God, ſhall the number of fifty cut off more then five? or ſhall leſs then ninety be alotted for four? Shall the Virgin be barren, and the Lyon have no iſſue? Shall leſs then 36 end in two? Shall the ſecond end in a Cipher? Shall ſeven come to be one, and then none? This is a Myſtery to many, yet true in its effects; part of which is exactly fulfilled, the reſt makes haſte, and in its time muſt conclude the Prophecy. I were able to produce other Preſidents of the like nature, but this ſhall ſerve to clear the Celeſtial Influences upon Families.</p>
               <p>Now I ſhall ſpeak briefly to the laſt particular, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Heavenly Bodies have a reſpect in their Influence to <hi>particular ones,</hi> to the Manifeſtation of thoſe ſeveral Occurrences which are, to befall them in this inferior world: For every ſingle man and woman, when they begin to have Being under a <hi>determinate Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendant</hi> and <hi>Heavenly Conſtellation,</hi> they receive with that Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a wonderful virtue of working and ſuffering, more then what it receives from its proper kind, by the Influence of the Heavens, from the obedience of the <hi>matter</hi> of the thing generable, which contains in it ſelf <hi>properties</hi> of the <hi>Elemental Virtues,</hi> with a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til <hi>ayral ſpirit,</hi> which makes the <hi>ſiminal matter</hi> fruitful, the which is apt to receive any impreſſion from the <hi>Celeſtial Virtues,</hi> and the Higher Powers diſpoſing the <hi>Elemental Properties,</hi> and doth inſtamp its <hi>virtue</hi> and <hi>form</hi> upon the <hi>generable matter,</hi> ſuitable to its correſpondency to the Celeſtial Souls, from the which ground the <hi>matter</hi> thus formed and diſpoſed, it comes to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to obedience unto thoſe Higher Powers; ſo that according to the <hi>motions</hi> of the Superiors and their Influences, divers effects, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations and behaviors are wrought, not only from the <hi>matter</hi> diverſly diſpoſed (as the moſt think) but from the diverſe Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Superiors, and their different forms; and the degrees of theſe are diverſly diſtributed of God, the firſt Cauſe of all, who remains the ſame, diſtributes to every one as he ſees good, to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117775:17"/> which the ſecondary Cauſes do co-operate, Angelical and Celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, in their diſpoſing of the <hi>corporal matter,</hi> and other things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them: So that from hence <hi>Aſtrologians</hi> ſay, That ſome men are <hi>Solar,</hi> and ſome men <hi>Mercurial,</hi> and ſo of the reſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that they have received in their beginnings, <hi>virtue</hi> and <hi>opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> from thoſe Bodies, in the correſpondency of their <hi>ſeminal matter</hi> with thoſe <hi>Stars,</hi> both in their <hi>bodies</hi> and <hi>inclinations,</hi> which ſhew themſelves more conſpicuouſly and powerful when the <hi>internal faculty</hi> hath attained its proper power and ſtrength, which it received at its firſt Being: So that <hi>inclinations</hi> and <hi>beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viors</hi> of all men do appear in their workings or ſufferings more or leſs, ſuitable to that <hi>virtue</hi> which they have received from the Superiors, and correſpond with them, ſo far forth as they rule thoſe <hi>properties;</hi> for in ſome men the <hi>virtue</hi> of the Celeſtial Souls are leſs drowned, and leſs incumbered with <hi>contrariety,</hi> and in ſuch that <hi>virtue</hi> is more conſpicuous and perfect then in others, which made the <hi>Platonicks</hi> to ſay, <hi>That Celeſtial Virtues were infuſed according to the deſert of the matter;</hi> which we ſee ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in Chriſt, who by reaſon of the purity and perfection of the <hi>corporal matter,</hi> it was capable to receive the fulneſs of the <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> in <hi>whom it dwelt</hi> (as the Scripture ſaith) <hi>bodily,</hi> the excellency of whoſe Perſon was manifeſted to the <hi>Magi</hi> at his <hi>Birth</hi> by that <hi>new Star</hi> which led them to his preſence to worſhip him, which was a <hi>Celeſtial Demonſtration</hi> of his <hi>Divine Deſcent:</hi> Not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to that was the <hi>Star</hi> in the time of <hi>Auguſtus Ceſar,</hi> in the which <hi>Sybillia Tiburtina</hi> ſhewed to the ſaid <hi>Auguſtus</hi> the Image of a <hi>beautiful Virgin,</hi> holding a Boy in her boſom, and ſaying, <hi>This Child is more noble and greater then thou, worſhip him.</hi> And according to the <hi>verification</hi> of ſome learned <hi>Authors,</hi> the <hi>Horo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcope</hi> of our <hi>Saviours Nativity</hi> was in the firſt Decade of <hi>Virgo,</hi> in the which before his <hi>Manifestation</hi> in the fleſh was a Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Saturn, Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> which did fore-ſhew his Birth: And according to the opinion of <hi>Albumazer,</hi> that in the ſame Decade of <hi>Virgo,</hi> aſcendeth a <hi>beautiful Virgin,</hi> of a <hi>comely Body, pleaſant Countenance, modeſt Attire, long Hair, holding two Plums in her hand, ſitting upon a golden Throne, and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Boy.</hi> And of the ſame opinion was <hi>Abraham,</hi> whoſe words
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117775:17"/> are theſe; <hi>There aſcendeth in the firſt face of Virgo a very fair Virgin, having long Hair, holding two ears of Corn in her hand, and ſhe ſitteth upon a ſeat, and nouriſhing a little Boy by giving him ſuck, and enciting him to eat:</hi> All which were nothing elſe but <hi>Angelical Manifestations</hi> of that <hi>purity</hi> and <hi>perfection</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> which was to be brought forth into the world in the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the which I think no ingenuous man will deny. But now I will proceed. Now becauſe of this <hi>inherent correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Property</hi> which the <hi>matter</hi> of the Body hath received from the <hi>ſuperior Powers</hi> and <hi>Virtues</hi> in its beginning of Being, it comes to be moved to thoſe ſeveral actions of <hi>paſſion,</hi> either of <hi>love</hi> or <hi>enmity,</hi> by the movings of the Superiors to the like, for in them it is firſt conceived, and ſo carried down by their Influence upon thoſe Bodies, that have a <hi>ſecret virtue</hi> of correſpondency, and a reciprocal <hi>property</hi> of embracing thoſe Influences; from whence I conceive that that part of <hi>Aſtrology</hi> hath its Ground which we call <hi>Horary Queſtions;</hi> for it is found by large experience, that when any perſon is moved really in his mind to any particular Act, and is carried out to propoſe a queſtion to an Artiſt, that then the Heavens and thoſe ſuperior Bodies do contain a true and real de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Act and its event, anſwerable to that operation or moving of the inferior mind of the perſon; for whatſoever is act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in and by man, is at firſt conceived in the Heavens, and ſo far a good <hi>experient Artiſt</hi> is not deceived; but when there is no ſuch moving in the Superiors, then there is no perfect moving or opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon or in the mind of a perſon, but imperfect, and ſuch as it is, doth ſometimes produce a ſlight deſire or will in the perſon to know ſomething, but what he knows not; and in this reſpect the Heavens give no demonſtration of the event, which in many young <hi>Artiſts</hi> hath been the cauſe (I fear) of thoſe many falſe Judgments, which ariſe from a want of a true knowledg and underſtanding of the minds of the Superiors, which Ignorance hath cauſed them to ſpeak their own <hi>thoughts</hi> for the ſence of the Heavens, as if they had all the ſuperior Bodies, with their ſeveral <hi>Intelligences</hi> in the bridle of their <hi>Pocket gain;</hi> but they ought to know, that thoſe Divine Powers are not ordained to ſerve men to ſuch baſe ends, whoſe fond preſumption is as great as <hi>Phaetons</hi> folly, who to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117775:18"/> himſelf of the linage of Heaven, produced his own overthrow, and others ruines: If you be the true ſons of <hi>Art,</hi> undertake no ſuch <hi>impoſſibilities,</hi> as to rule the Heavenly Powers with the reins of your own fancies. I ſpeak this to thoſe young <hi>Students,</hi> who are (I am afraid) not well acquainted with the <hi>natural Motion</hi> of the <hi>Orbs,</hi> much leſs with thoſe <hi>excellent Powers</hi> that are Rulers of them under the firſt Cauſe. And not only of them alone, but of the Terreſtial world in their due order, for a certain limit of time, appointed by the Wiſdom of that chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Good, who made all things in form and order, and doth by his Power, given forth to thoſe his Celeſtial Miniſters, govern it in the like form and order, to the ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth of his Majeſty, Glory, Power, and infinite Wiſdom; and every Age from the beginning is found by obſervation to have had ſome kind of reſpect in their actions to the nature of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel or Spirit then Ruling, ſuitable to the capacity of thoſe then go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned; and if I miſtake not, we in this preſent Age are under the Rule of <hi>Raphael,</hi> which is the cauſe (according to the <hi>determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the firſt Cauſe) of thoſe abundant Sects, Opinions, Hereſies, Fancies of the brain <hi>Disputes, Contentions, Subtilty, Falſhood, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſtability,</hi> cunning and <hi>witty Policy,</hi> and the like, of all which the former Ages knew not the like: This is a great Myſtery to moſt, and a thing not perfect to any; I mean, the true knowledg of this Angelical Rule, the which our Reaſons are not able to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend up unto, but hath been found out by obſervation of ſome in former Ages, and the experience of ſome of late, learned in the moſt occult Powers of Nature. And a Myſtery not inferior to this, is that <hi>ſecret virtue</hi> and <hi>admirable ſignification</hi> that is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly known by long experience to be in thoſe twelve Diviſions of the Heavens, called the <hi>twelve Manſions</hi> or Houſes of Heaven, and have relation to all things appertaining to the life, quality, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of every one in what relation ſoever he may or can be; the which <hi>ſecret virtue</hi> in the Heavens is hid from the eyes of our Reaſon, though the virtue, power and ſignification of them are dayly found by experience, which is no ſtrange thing that our Reaſon ſhould not fathom the depth thereof to find the Cauſe and Ground: For we ſee the manifeſtation of the virtue of the Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone in a viſible <hi>attraction</hi> of Iron to it ſelf, but know not the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117775:18"/> Cauſe thereof: And ſuch <hi>virtues</hi> the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> called <hi>hidden Qualities,</hi> becauſe the Cauſes of them are hid, ſo that mans underſtanding cannot find them out no ways, but long obſervation and experience hath found out many things of the like Nature, which Search and Reaſon could not attain. As for inſtance; We ſee that in the ſtomack the meat that we eat is digeſted by heat, which we truly know, ſo it is trans<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ormed by a <hi>ſecret virtue,</hi> which we know not, but not by heat; for then why not at the fire, as well as in the ſtomack? but that of a certain it is transform-into a due nouriſhment of the Body, by what virtue we are not able to find. So alſo it is reported, that the <hi>Eaſtridg</hi> concocts cold and moſt hard Iron, and digeſts it into a due nouriſhment of its body, whoſe ſtomack (as it is reported) is not hurt with hot Iron: So the <hi>Echenes</hi> ſtops the ſhip, and the <hi>Salamander</hi> abides the fire without hurt, and the <hi>Amber</hi> draws all things to it except Baſil: theſe are the works of hidden Virtues, which we admire and are amazed at, as unknown to us in reſpect of their Cauſes; but our experience doth find the viſible working, and the effects of thoſe <hi>ſecret</hi> and <hi>occult properties.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I hope, gentle Reader, by this, that this excellent <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy</hi> is no ſuch thing as the world thinks it to be, nor as that ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous <hi>Pamphlet</hi> terms it; thou ſeeſt it clear from the jealouſie of a <hi>Diabolical Agent;</hi> in it there is no workings by a combination with the power of the dark world, but to be wholy celeſtial and divine. And although ſome men have abuſed it to baſe ends, by the inſtigation of the Devil, and hath bewitched ſome fancies, and and led them to Idolatry as a Doctrine of Religion, and corrupted the word <hi>Aſtrology</hi> by giving a divine Power to the Stars which they have not, that is, an independing Power of themſelves, and ſo have been eſteemed as gods, and not as Inſtruments ſet up by the firſt Cauſe; all which I contemn; but the abuſe of the thing takes not away the Art, conſidering that the Heavenly Bodies have and do exerciſe their virtues upon the Inferiors: For it is vulgarly known to thoſe who have but the ſmalleſt knowledg of the Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial Bodies, That the Sun and Star of <hi>Mars</hi> doth dry, the Moon doth moiſten, and govern the Tydes of the Sea, that <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> doth produce winds, and <hi>Saturn</hi> dark and obſcure wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117775:19"/> and that the ſtars do differ in magnitude, and to all the ſtars God hath given their proper names, which had they hot influences and virtues different they need not. And as it is Lawful in all the parts of it, as I have ſpoken before:</p>
               <p>So alſo it is moſt Ancient, and was practiſed by the moſt good and holieſt men. For <hi>Cham</hi> the ſon of <hi>Noah,</hi> who (as <hi>Caſſianus</hi> reporteth) was knowing not only in this Art, but in all the ſeven Libral Sciences, who having a fore-knowledg of the Univerſal Flood, that he might preſerve his <hi>attainments</hi> to after Ages, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graved them in 14 Pillars, ſeven of Brick to reſiſt the injury of fire, and ſeven of Braſs to oppoſe the force of water; all which others conceive were known to that juſt and holy man <hi>Noah,</hi> and left by him to his ſons. So alſo <hi>Abraham,</hi> that righteous man (as <hi>Joſephus</hi> reports) was very much learned in theſe Arts, more then any other in that Age, if he did not abundantly exceed them all, differing from the wiſdom of after Times in this, that he knew and acknowledged the true Cauſe and Giver of life and virtue to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and all natural things; whereas others forgetting this, adored the Inſtruments or ſecond Cauſes, and did attribute proper ſtrength to the things themſelves, from which the effects were ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, which belongs to that Wiſdom, which being one, and remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in it ſelf, can do all things, and reneweth all. And <hi>Eupolemon</hi> doth affirm, That <hi>Abraham,</hi> the holieſt and wiſeſt of men, did firſt teach the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> then the <hi>Phenitians,</hi> and laſtly the <hi>Egyptian Prieſts,</hi> Aſtrology and Divine Knowledg; and that he did (as <hi>Philo</hi> ſaith) diligently contemplate the Heavens, which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſeemeth to hint out, in the promiſe of God to him concerning the <hi>multiplicity</hi> of his Seed. So alſo that good man <hi>Jacob</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood that the <hi>Sun</hi> (in the dream of <hi>Joſeph</hi>) had ſignification of himſelf, and that the <hi>Moon</hi> was meant his wife, and the <hi>eleven Stars</hi> his ſons. Alſo <hi>Job,</hi> that juſt man, was verſed in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the ſtars, where he denominateth the names of <hi>Arturus, Orion,</hi> and <hi>Pleiades,</hi> and alſo the diviſions of the Heavens and Earth in thoſe words, <hi>and the Climates of the South;</hi> ſo that when God pleaded his own Power and Greatneſs, he uſeth the ſame Stars or Conſtellations to convince <hi>Job</hi> with, and alſo doth declare their Influence upon the Elementary Properties, for ſaith he, <hi>Canſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117775:19"/> thou reſtrain the ſweet Influence of the Pleiades, or unlooſe the bands of Orion? Canſt thou guide Arturus and his ſons?</hi> What the product of their Influence there meant, let all <hi>Commenters</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, and all ſuch as have received a prejudice againſt this lawful Art contemplate in their minds. So likewiſe <hi>Moſes,</hi> a man of God, was verſed excellently in all the learning of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> who were a people that were moſt rare in the knowledg of theſe Arts, more then any other Nations whatſoever. So <hi>Daniel</hi> and the <hi>three Children,</hi> it is ſaid, That <hi>the King found them ten times better then all the Magicians and Astrologers that were in his Realm;</hi> which had they not been knowing in both thoſe Sciences, they would not have been compared with them, for always a wiſe man maketh compariſons in things of a like nature; and how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable and unjuſt would the Decree have been, that <hi>Daniel</hi> and his fellows ſhould have been ſlain, with the reſt of the <hi>Wiſe men of Babel,</hi> had not they been Profeſſors of the ſame Sciences? For the Scripture ſaith, That <hi>the Decree went forth, that the Wiſe men ſhould be ſlain; and they ſought after Daniel and his fellows to ſlay them with the reſt.</hi> And <hi>Solomon,</hi> the wiſeſt of men, was excellently acquainted with the <hi>natural virtues</hi> of things, alſo in their operations and effects, with their ſeveral Times and Seaſons, for to every action and thing there is a time appointed by the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Wiſdom and Fore-knowledg of the firſt Cauſe, the which time and ſeaſon in reference to means and event is either good or evil, not that there is any evil in <hi>Time</hi> it ſelf, but in reſpect of thoſe many effects that are by certain means to be produced, for all things and actions are manifeſted in their due times and ſeaſons, ſo that all things follow in their kind each other by a certain <hi>eternal conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity,</hi> and in this regard <hi>Time</hi> comes to be termed <hi>good</hi> or <hi>evil:</hi> For this is clear, that all creatures have their ſeaſons of beginning of life, motion, ſtrength, &amp;c. but not all at one and the ſame time. So in the Heavens, all things and actions, which are to be brought to paſs here below, are not conceived in the minds of the Celeſtial Souls at one and the ſame time, but anſwerable to thoſe times and ſeaſons in the which they are to be manifeſted here in this inferior world; and therefore for any to expect to have a demonſtration from the Heavens of future events before their ſeaſon, ſhall and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117775:20"/> muſt acknowledg that he looked for it in an evil time.</p>
               <p>And thus have I given thee, Ingenuous Reader, an <hi>Impartial Account</hi> of the Lawfulneſs of both theſe <hi>Arts,</hi> which is the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent apprehenſion that I have of them, according to that ſmall mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of knowledg that I have attained to in my private ſtudy, which is but as it were of yeſterday, and the firſt of this nature that I ever attempted to commit to writing, which indeed was drawn from me by the importunity of ſome private friends, who are well-wiſhers to theſe <hi>excellent Arts,</hi> though but ſecretly for their own private Exerciſe and Recreation; for my own part, did I but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend upon a real Experiment, that there were in the true and ſubſtantial Grounds of this <hi>Art</hi> any evil and Diabolical Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, I would be the firſt that ſhould according to my weak abilities manifeſt it to the world; for I am one that as to any <hi>Art</hi> am not ſo taken with a blind affection, that to conclude it to be abſolute and lawful for my affection ſake, but can and will refrain the Study of any Art or Science, of the which my Reaſon and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment is convinced, to be unlawful, and not convenient for a Chriſtians Exerciſe. I profeſs, I had not appeared in Print, had not that ſmall <hi>Pamphlet</hi> been ſo long without an Anſwer; and though it doth not contain any ſolid Argument againſt either of theſe <hi>Arts,</hi> yet ſuch is the fond prejudice that many in <hi>England</hi> hath taken againſt them, that they are ready to conclude that it is indeed ſo as that Book reports, and alſo that I might draw forth ſome more able then my ſelf to vindicate theſe <hi>Arts,</hi> and it is very probable that which I have done toward that end may find cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures from many: Some may call me a <hi>Star-gazer;</hi> I tell thee whatſoever thou art, I can ſee thy folly and ignorance in the leaſt ſtar, and thy great Creators Glory in the ſmalleſt beam: Others may ſay, That <hi>of a Christian I am become a Diſciple to Plato;</hi> I profeſs I cannot ſee one ſeat in his School for thy ignorance, whoſe common Precepts were more divine then thy beſt Profeſſion, and ſuch as thou who termeſt thy ſelf a Chriſtian not capable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive. And for my ſelf, I deſire truly to be <hi>Philoſopher</hi> in the right knowledg of the Cauſe of Cauſes; to be a <hi>Platonick,</hi> in a true apprehenſion of the Angelical and Intelectual World; to be a <hi>Star-gazer,</hi> ſo that I may really contemplate the Heavens, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117775:20"/> Celeſtial Bodies; to be a <hi>Stoick,</hi> to attain a great meaſure of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience; to be a <hi>Hermet,</hi> as to the incombrances of the world; and yet to be a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> in the true reception of the benefit of my Saviours Paſſion, which is the way for me to my Perfection.</p>
               <p>And therefore to all you <hi>Students</hi> in <hi>Magick</hi> and <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> ſee that you walk humbly with your God, be not proud of your <hi>attainments,</hi> for you have received them; have a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in your walkings toward men, ſo ſhall you be more able to operate truly in theſe <hi>Arts;</hi> labour to reduce your ſpirits into the form &amp; likeneſs of thoſe Celeſtial Powers, and then you may receive divine Power and Virtue from them; and ſtudy to know thy Creator in all thoſe abundance of Creatures that thou ſeeſt ſcatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up and down in the world, in which more or leſs of his Glory and Brightneſs doth reſide, and then how happy wilt thou be: Let not Covetouſneſs overſway thy Judgment, and then both theſe <hi>Arts</hi> will be Honorable, in ſpight of all Oppoſers. This is all that I have to write as to this preſent <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> and ſo ſubſcribe my ſelf to be,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Thine, <hi>H. W.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>From my private Chamber in <hi>London,</hi>
                     <date> the nineth of <hi>Novemb. 1650.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
